Inventory to the Records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP) (1970-1985)
Sophia Smith Collection
Interview with Illinois Representative Donald Deuster. He discusses his beliefs that the ERA is harmful to women, his opinion of "equal pay for equal work" and the Fourteenth Amendment, how his anti-ERA stance affected his political career and personal life, why he believes the ERA will fail, and his oppositional strategies.
#21, "Fighting for the Obvious: Interview with Rep. Donald Deuster (anti-ERA), #22, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Representative Donald Deuster. He discusses what the ERA would change, Gerald and Betty Ford's opinions on the ERA, the labor leaders' initial opposition to the ERA, the most effective tactics in stopping the ERA (including associating it with homosexuality and abortion), and the pro-ERA media bias.
#22, "Fighting for the Obvious: Interview with Rep. Donald Deuster (anti-ERA), #23, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Representative Donald Deuster. He discusses his personal reactions to the Illinois ERA campaign, what he believes are the strongest and weakest elements of the pro-ERA campaign in Illinois (the mayor's involvement), and how he feels about the men and women who have been fighting on both sides of the ERA issue.
#23, "Fighting for the Obvious: Interview with Rep. Donald Deuster (anti-ERA), #24, n.d."
Continuing footage of the interview with Representative Donald Deuster. He discusses his respect for the pro-ERA campaign, the rights women have lost as a result of the courts (i.e. divorce), his views on maternity/paternity leave, and why he believes the ERA will not pass ("because the people don't want it"). Footage then shows photographs of the Deuster family. Two ERA supporters discussing police brutality and intimidation against demonstrators, and the Grassroots Group of Second Class Citizens.
"Then the proponents came down with roses, so on the floor of the House, everybody who voted for ERA would get a rose, and that's a very feminine thing - to show that they're not lesbians and homosexuals, or they don't hate men; they're full of love and affection; they bring us roses." - Representative Donald Deuster
#24, "Fighting for the Obvious: Linda Miller NOW meeting re: student rally day #10," n.d.
Footage shows Linda Miller and other NOW members discussing plans and tactics for their student activists' rally day at the Springfield legislature.
#25, "Fighting for the Obvious: Lunatic Fringe, Alice and Bernice #25, n.d."
Interview with Bernice (?) She discusses the potential outcomes of the ERA's failure, the way the media portrays the women's movement, the tactics and strategies of the ERA movement, the women who fast in support of the ERA, and the ratification process. The last seven minutes of film shows various antique photographs.
#26, "Fighting for the Obvious: Lunatic Fringe, Alice and Bernice #26, n.d."
Interview with Alice (?) She discusses the sit-in she organized and participated in at the Illinois Senate building, their subsequent police removal, and their singing of "We Shall Not Be Moved."
#27, "Fighting for the Obvious: Anne Courtney interview #27, 1982"
Footage begins with Anne Courtney and Clara Johnston sitting on a front porch and walking down the street together. Footage then shifts to Anne Courtney discussing her involvement in the women's movement since 1973, her leadership of her local Illinois NOW chapter and ERA coalition, how she became a feminist, her involvement with Betty Freidan, what ratification struggle has taught her, and why so many women have been so highly committed to the fight for the ERA.
#28, "Fighting for the Obvious: Anne Courtney interview #28, 1982"
Continuing footage of the interview with Anne Courtney. She discusses the painful lessons the ERA fight has taught her, her friendships with other feminists, the manipulative nature of legislators, and what about the ERA struggle makes her angriest.
#29, "Fighting for the Obvious: Anne Courtney interview #29," 1982
*Sound does not work from the 3-minute to the 5-minute mark.
Continuing footage of Anne Courtney. She discusses the worst experience she ever had while lobbying a legislator. Footage then shifts to an interview with Clara Johnston. She explains how long she has worked on the ERA campaign, what made her realize the fight for the ERA was so important, why she believes politicians don't take the ERA seriously, the thing that makes her angriest about the ERA struggle, and how pained it makes her to think that she will never live in a society where women are equal to men under the Constitution.
#30, "Fighting for the Obvious: Clara Johnston interview #30," 1982
Continuing footage of Clara Johnston. She discusses examples of sexism she has experienced at her job, her experiences with Prescott Bloom (a Senator from her district; R-Peoria), what she believes has motivated so many women to fight for the ERA, what keeps her fighting year after year, and what she believes will happen to the women's movement if the ERA is not ratified.
#31, "Fighting for the Obvious: Clara Johnston interview #31, 1982"
Interview with Clara Johnston. She discusses the main differences between anti- and pro-ERA women, why anti-ERA women make her so angry, how to channel the anger that will result from the ERA's defeat, the best thing she has learned from the struggle for ERA, why women's rights are commonly ignored by male activists, and why it will be impossible for women to return to a mindset prior to the ERA struggle.
#32, "Fighting for the Obvious: Students on the bus #32," n.d.
Footage shows students on a bus ride to Springfield to protest and lobby at the Illinois legislature. Older NOW members, including Debbie Harvey, instruct the students on how to approach and address legislators, strategies for forming and presenting their arguments, and the history of the ERA and women's rights struggle.
#33, "Fighting for the Obvious: Students on the bus #33,"n.d.
*Video does not work from 4:08-minute mark to 5:40-minute mark.
Footage of student lobbyists on a bus to Springfield practicing their presentations. NOW members give the students advice on how to talk to the legislators. Footage then shows the students outside of the legislative building and inside, talking to various legislators.
#34, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #34," n.d.
Continuing footage of the NOW/student bus ride to Springfield. NOW members give the students more advice on how to handle anti-ERA legislators.
#35, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #35," n.d.
*Sound does not work from the 4:30 mark to the 6:35 mark, 7:20 to 7:50
Footage shows students from the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana and Eastern Illinois University. The students discuss their strategies for approaching legislators, the problems with the 3/5 rule, and which politicians specifically to target. The footage then shifts to the rally at the legislature.
#36, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #36," n.d.
*Sound does not work until the 9:35-minute mark.
Footage shows ERA supporters and protestors in the Illinois legislature. Dr. Dale, a professor at Illinois State University, and Illinois Representative Susan Catania (R) give speeches in support of the ERA and women's rights. Catania's speech includes Canada's constitutional equal rights clause and the history of the Illinois women's movement.
#37, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #37," n.d.
Continuing footage of Representative Susan Catania's speech at the Illinois legislature. Other speakers include Jeannie Morris, TV sports reporter/CBS correspondent, Mary Jean Collins, co-director of the NOW ERA campaign, and Monica Faith Stewart, State Representative from Chicago's 29th district, gives a speech urging young women to continue to be politically involved.
#38, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #38," n.d.
Footage of a pro-ERA rally. Representative John Donne (D) and Senator James Taylor give speeches urging the ERA supporters to let the governor know how they feel. Representative Barbara Flynn-Curry also criticizes Illinois Governor Thompson
#39, "Fighting for the Obvious: Student rally #39," n.d.
*Video does not work until the 1:34-minute mark.
DVD includes much of the same footage as #37. More footage of pro-ERA songs. Also, Mary Jean Collins urges the audience (mostly students) to help with the ERA Countdown Campaign.
#40, "Fighting for the Obvious: Monica's Student Interview #40," n.d.
Partially repeated footage from #39. More pro-ERA songs (same as those featured on #38). Footage then shifts to two young women outside of the legislature explaining why the support the ERA.
#41, "Fighting for the Obvious: Students on the bus #41," n.d.
Continuing footage from #40. More interviews with young women about why they are at the legislature fighting for the ERA, their attitudes towards the legislators and their experiences interacting with them. The DVD ends footage of the activists boarding the bus, then shows them sharing their positive and negative experiences at the legislature.
#42, "Fighting for the Obvious: Students on the bus #42," n.d.
Continuing footage of the student activists discussing their experiences speaking to elected officials at the legislature.
#43, "Fighting for the Obvious: Students on the bus #43," n.d.
Continuing footage of DVDs #42 and #43; student activists on their way home from the Illinois legislature.
#44, "Fighting for the Obvious: Chicago phone bank re rally #44," n.d.
Footage of Marilyn Stuckey from the ERA Countdown Campaign calling people urging them to participate in the June 6th rally, or
#45, "Fighting for the Obvious: IL NOW rally #45," n.d.
Footage shows NOW volunteers making signs and banners for the June 6th, 1982 ERA rally at the Illinois State House.
#46, "Fighting for the Obvious: IL NOW rally #46," n.d.
Footage filmed at the Illinois NOW Headquarters. NOW members are shown calling people to ask them if they will be attending the June 6th rally, discussing plans for the June 6th rally, and discussing the sources of their monetary contributions.
#47, "Fighting for the Obvious: IL NOW rally #47," n.d.
Continuing footage of the Illinois NOW Headquarters. Some NOW members discuss budget and expenses and others are shown painting signs and posters for the upcoming rally. The video is also interspersed with footage of a construction worker fixing the roof of a house.
#48, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rebellion #48," n.d.
Footage shows the ERA rally at the Illinois State House. NOW members and other volunteers set up banners, check in guests and speakers, and discuss the agenda for the rally, and there are some group sing-a-longs in the lobby of the State House. The DVD also includes part of an interview with roofing workers.
#49, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rebellion #49," n.d."
*Sound does not work from the 12:15-minute mark to the 13:15-minute mark.
Continuing footage of the IL State House rally. Various people give feminist and pro-ERA speeches to the crowd.
#50, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rebellion #50," n.d.
Continuing footage of the rally. More speeches, sing-a-longs, including "We Shall Not Be Moved." Also, several of the protestors chain themselves together inside of the legislature.
#51, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rebellion #51," n.d.
*Sound does not work from the 2:19-minute mark to the 12:03-minute mark.
Continuing footage of the rally. More singing in the Senate gallery of "We Shall Not Be Moved" and other protest songs. Protestors are also shown repeatedly chanting, "ERA Yes, 3/5 Now."
#52, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rebellion #52," n.d.
Continuing footage of the rally. Once again, female protestors are shown chained together in protest. A woman named Jennifer Klindt discusses why she is a feminist, her sexual assault/rape at age sixteen, how she first become involved with activism, and the personal sacrifices she has had to make in order to participate in the fight for the ERA. The DVD ends with footage of carpenters working.
#53, "Fighting for the Obvious: Jennifer Klindt interview #53," n.d.
Continuing footage of the interview with Jennifer Klindt. She discusses what she believes are the "sad" aspects of feminism, what she has learned from her activist work, and outlines some of the difficulties that women face as a result of feminism.
#54, "Fighting for the Obvious: Jennifer Klindt interview #54," n.d.
*Sound stops working at the 15:30-minute mark.
More footage of the chained protestors in the Illinois legislature, singing protest songs, including "Bread and Roses." The DVD then shifts back to footage of Jennifer Klindt. She talks about her choice to work within the legislative system to try to enact change, the lobbying strategies of the pro-ERA movement, and her son's reaction to the ERA's defeat.
#55, "Fighting for the Obvious: Fasters interview #55," 1982
*Audio and video stop working at the 14:30-minute mark.
Footage shows "Women Hunger for Justice" convened in the Illinois legislature, on Day #21 of their fast. One of the fasters expresses the group public statement they issued on their first day of fasting. Another woman talks about why female fasters are viewed as "inappropriate," what keeps them going, the power of fasting, what they have learned from the experience, and the message they would like to leave for posterity. The DVD ends with some brief footage of factory workers.
#56, "Fighting for the Obvious: Fasters interview #56," 1982
Continuing footage of the "Women Hunger for Justice" interviews (still on Day #21 of their fast). They consider what lessons there are to be learned from the difficulties of the ERA struggle, how to focus on women's power, and how to challenge sexism. The DVD concludes with footage of anti-ERA demonstrators. The last :43 seconds is silent footage of a man doing wall construction.
#57, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rally #57," 1982
Footage shows women at an Illinois pro-ERA march/rally, signing into a rally, getting off of buses, talking in small groups, singing songs, distributing buttons, and generally preparing for the march. Anne Courtney (leader of a local Illinois NOW chapter) is also included in the footage.
#58, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rally #58," 1982
* Sound levels are consistently uneven.
Continuing footage of the Illinois pro-ERA march/rally. Clips of pro-ERA songs and pre-march announcements, then footage shifts to footage of the march itself. Someone mentions that there are an estimated 15,000 people at the march. (The last few seconds of the DVD show the roofing construction man).
#59, "Fighting for the Obvious: Balcony, MJ Collins, Catania, Taylor, Smeal #59," 1982
Continuing footage of the march/rally. There are more songs and speeches, including remarks by Mary-Jean Collins, the co-director of NOW's Countdown Campaign, Illinois Representative Susan Catania, and NOW National President Ellie Smeal.
#60, "Fighting for the Obvious: Smeal, Byrne, Ford #60," 1982
Continuing footage of the rally, including the end of Ellie Smeal's speech, a speech by Jane Byrne, Chicago's first female mayor of Chicago, and former First Lady Betty Ford.
#61, "Fighting for the Obvious: Maureen #61," 1982
Continuing footage of the rally. Sister Maureen Fiedler gives a speech about the pro-ERA movement, their fasting, and the current status of the ERA bill.
#62, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rally #62," 1982
Continuing footage of the rally. More of the fasters give speeches and public statements. "The Ballad of the ERA" and other songs are performed.
#63, "Fighting for the Obvious: Rally #63," 1982
*Video does not work correctly from the :40-minute mark to the 1:18-minute mark.
*Sound does not work from the 3:50-minute mark to the 15:15-minute mark.
More songs are performed, including "This Little Light of Mine" and "We Will Never Give Up, We Will Never Give In." Video then shifts to silent footage of the fasters in the legislature (still day #21 of their fast). Paramedics attend to an ill faster and take her away on a stretcher. When the sound returns, there is a continuation of the song "We Will Never Give Up."
#64, "Fighting for the Obvious: Committee of the Whole ERA debate, reel #1 (#64)," n.d.
*Sound does not work from the 3:47-minute mark to the 6:47-minute mark.
More footage of protestors inside the legislature. More singing of "We Shall Overcome" and the parody, "Are You Sleeping, Illinois?" inside the House of Representatives Guest Gallery. Then, there is silent footage of protestors congregated within the legislature. When the sound returns, there is more chanting and singing by both pro-ERA activists ("ERA, Always") and anti-ERA protestors ("ERA, Go Away").
#65, "Fighting for the Obvious: Committee of the Whole ERA debate, reel #2 (#65)," n.d.
*Video goes blank from 13:45-minute mark to the 14:17-minute mark.
Footage of a legislative hearing of the Committee of the Whole of the House of Representatives. Republican Governor Jim Thompson gives a speech in favor of the ERA in front of the General Assembly, as does NOW President Ellie Smeal. Robert Gibson, head of the Illinois AFL-CIO, also speaks in favor of the ERA, as does a representative of the American Bar Association.
#66, "Fighting for the Obvious: Committee of the Whole ERA Debate, reel #3 (#66)," n.d."
Continuing footage of the legislative hearing. A variety of religious leaders give pro-ERA speeches, including an Illinois priest, a nun from the Sisters of Charity of the Blessed Virgin Mary, and the Chairperson-Elect of the Leadership Conference of Women Religious. On the anti-ERA side, Eliza Haskell, the founding member of the Atlanta NOW chapter describes herself as "a feminist opposed to the ERA." Several young women from Chicago also speak out against the ERA, including a 19-year-old teacher who describes being opposed to the potential of being drafted for military service.
#67, "Fighting for the Obvious: Committee of the Whole ERA Debate, reel #4 (#67)," n.d.
Continuing footage of the legislative hearing. More young women speak against being drafted and military conscription. Phyllis Schlafly gives a speech against the ERA, specifically, tax-funded abortions, the Hyde Amendment, the draft, and describes the ERA as "the greatest take away of rights in history." Another woman argues that God made women different from men, therefore illegitimating the ERA's purpose. Reverend William Schroeder argues against the draft and granting the federal government more powers. Representatives ask some of the speakers questions.
#68, "Fighting for the Obvious: Committee of the Whole ERA Deabte, reel #5 (#68)," n.d.
*Video stops working.
Footage switches from continued footage of the hearing to clips from a pro-ERA protest. The video then stops working, and audio plays of Kristen Lems, singer-songwriter, playing ERA songs, such as "Ballad of the ERA," and "We Will Never Give Up, We Will Never Give In." The DVD ends with footage of men talking at a dinner party.
#69, "Fighting for the Obvious: House cutaways, Catania (#69)," 1982
Continuing footage of the hearing, and more assorted testimonies. The ERA is read aloud, Susan Catania gives a speech addressing the draft issue and other facets of the ERA. The DVD ends with an interview of an unidentified male filmmaker.
#70, "Fighting for the Obvious: Ellie Smeal at the Y; Ellie's interview, Ellie's cutaways (#70)," n.d.
Footage shows a meeting of several NOW metropolitan chapters. Linda Miller (co-chair of the ERA Countdown Campaign) and Ellie Smeal (president of NOW) give statements.
#71, "Fighting for the Obvious: Ellie Smeal at the Y; Ellie's interview, Ellie's cutaways (#71)," n.d.
Footage shows speech given in Illinois by Ellie Smeal. Topics include: Mayor Bunn; upcoming rally on 6/6; Illinois' final vote for the ratification of the ERA amendment; FL Governor Grahm; conservative estimations of support; economic issues and gender gap of Reagan support.
#72, "Fighting for the Obvious: Ellie Smeal at the Y; Ellie's interview, Ellie's cutaways (#72)," n.d.
Continuation of speech from the previous dvd. Topic include: insurance discrimination; the Farmer's Bureau; cases that NOW are litigating to prove gender bias; gender bias in social security.
Additional materials documenting the Equal Rights Amendment can be found in the papers of the Blake Family, Dori Jacobson, Dorothy Kenyon, Alma Lutz, G.J. Stillson MacDonnell, Gloria Steinem, Linda Stout, Mary van Kleeck, the records of the Young Women's Christian Association, and the Women's Rights and Employment Collections. The majority of the records of the National Organization for Women and the ERA can be found at the Schlesinger Library at Harvard University.
- SERIES I. ERACAP ADMINISTRATION(1981-85), .5 linear ft.
  This series contains Beth Leopold's administrative records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project, including the project proposal, ERACAP's financial and equipment needs, and correspondence with the Sophia Smith Collection. Most of the unrelated publications by history organizations and guides to oral histories have been removed from the collection.
- SERIES II. NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN AND THE ERA(1970-83), 2.25 linear ft.
  Beth Leopold's work at the National Organization for Women is documented in this series. Media projects played a large role in NOW's efforts to pass the ERA in the fifteen states where it hadn't yet passed. The ERA Countdown campaign materials include photocopies of images dating back to the early twentieth century that were selected for a film to document the struggle for the ERA, with the bulk of the images covering the 1970s and early 1980s. Other media-related projects for NOW can be found in the materials related to the Legal Defense and Education Fund. This series also covers several major marches and rallies for the ERA. The Capitol March for ERA focuses mostly on Chicago, where Leopold directed her energies. This series also includes subject files, memorabilia, and a bibliography of newspaper clippings from the New York Times related to the ERA from 1970 through 1982.
- SERIES III. WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY? DOCUMENTARY FILES(1974-82), 2 linear ft.
  This series is composed of the administrative and subject files of Victoria Costello, the director for Who Will Protect the Family?, an hour length color PBS documentary that examines the motivations, beliefs, and larger goals of the two movements fighting for and against the Equal Rights Amendment, focusing in particular on anti-ERA activist, Marilyn DeVries. And pro-ERA activist, Beth McAllister. Although the documentary specifically focuses on the three year battle to pass the ERA in North Carolina, the materials in this series relate to legislation, statistics, and organizations on both the state and national levels, as well as subjects that extend beyond the Equal Rights Amendment. Only a few transcripts from the film footage are in the collection; nevertheless, the few that exist provide valuable insight into the motivations of individuals fighting for and against the passage of the amendment, as do the brief summaries of selected footage in the Appendix. The audiovisual materials from the documentary are found in SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES IV. ERA DEFEAT(1982-84), .25 linear ft.
  This small series contains published and unpublished articles and essays that examine the Equal Rights Amendment, its defeat, and its supporters and opponents.
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS(1978-82), 17 linear ft.
  This large series forms the bulk of the collection and includes 30 hours of videotape for Fighting for the Obvious (over 100 tapes), a documentary about the ERA fight in Illinois, as well as several hundred ¾ inch Umatics and ½ inch Betas from the PBS documentary Who Will Protect the Family?, which documents the ERA fight in North Carolina.